Peter Mühlbacher

muehlbacher.peter@gmail.com | (+43) 660 3409620 | http://peter.muehlbacher.me

in: peter-muehlbacher | : petermuehlbacher

SUMMARY

Ph.D. candidate trained in mathematics and physics, with strong interdisciplinary skills developed from extensive collaboration with international research groups and ability to work independently or as part of a team.

Special expertise in the following areas:

Statistics Monte Carlo Simulations Data Analysis Probabilistic Forecasting

Quantum Mechanics
 High-dimensional Probability Theory

<u>Public track record</u> of my probabilistic predictions on Covid, economics, etc.
Investigated a potential "arbitrage" opportunity by analysing historical data

EDUCATION

EDUCATION	
Warwick University, Coventry, UK Ph.D, Mathematics Expected July Concentrations: Probability Theory, Quantum Spin Systems, Monte Carlo Simulations	2022
Cambridge University, Cambridge, UK MASt., Mathematics Concentrations: Probability Theory, Mathematical Physics	2017
Vienna University , Vienna, Austria BSc., Mathematics	2016
EXPERIENCE	
Dissertation Research Dissertation: "Probabilistic Methods for Quantum Spin Systems" • Designed algorithms to efficiently sample from high-dimensional distributions • Taught in part master's/Ph.D courses on Quantum Mechanics and Statistical Mechanics • Collaborated & co-authored papers with groups based in Europe, America, and Asia • Presented original research at international conferences with 50—500 attendees	2018-2022
 Unicredit Bank Austria (risk management) Analysed & advised on the implementation of an EU regulation Communicated amendments to this implementation to the Austrian Financial Market Authority 	2018
 Institute for Science & Technology (Vienna) Awarded the OeAD research scholarship (€2200) and a paid internship (acceptance rate: 3%) Published a paper on Random Matrix Theory 	2016—2018
Institute for Quantum Optics and Quantum Information (Vienna) • Assisted with study design, to be carried out by the European Space Agency	2015–2016
Paramedic • Full-time from July to March, on a voluntary basis afterwards	2013—2014
 Webdesign and Databases Developed several companies' websites Deployed HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, and SQL 	2008–2012
Forecasting on Metaculus	2021—present

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

- P. Mühlbacher, "Split-and-Merge in Stationary Random Stirring on General Graphs", pending publication.
- Found a new way of sampling from high-dimensional distributions and used it to improve state-of-the-art results
- P. Mühlbacher, "A New Loop Algorithm with Theoretical Implications", pending publication.
- Introduced a novel Monte Carlo algorithm for quantum spin systems and used it to prove new results
- Subject to further investigation with a group in Germany
- Presented in Mannheim (online)
- J. Björnberg, P. Mühlbacher, B. Nachtergaele, D. Ueltschi, "Dimerization in Quantum Spin Chains with O(n) Symmetry", Communications in Mathematical Physics volume 387, pages 1151–1189 (2021)
- Employed a delicate cluster expansion to prove surprising results about quantum spins
- "This is a fabulous paper. Congratulations" ~ Elliott Lieb (Princeton)
- Presented at <u>ICMP</u>, in Italy (and at Harvard by B. Nachtergaele)
- P. Mühlbacher, "Critical parameters for loop and Bernoulli percolation", ALEA volume 18, pages 289–308 (2021)
- Proved an open conjecture about comparisons between different probabilistic models
- Presented in Venice, Milton Keynes, Warsaw, Bristol
- L. Erdős, P. Mühlbacher, "Bounds on the Norm of Wigner-type Random Matrices", Random Matrices: Theory and Applications, volume 08 (2019)
- Used graphical representations & results from Computer Science to prove bounds on Random Matrices
- Presented in Montréal, Vienna, Warwick, Dortmund
- P. Mühlbacher, "Gaussian Free Field and Liouville Quantum Gravity", 2017
- Cambridge master's thesis, 87% (α-grade standard)
- P. Mühlbacher, "Diffusion Maps", 2015
- Bachelor thesis on dimensionality reduction and numerical methods for stochastic partial differential equations
- Awarded highest possible mark
- P. Mühlbacher, "High Dimensional Landscapes and Random Matrices", 2016
- Bachelor thesis on large deviations of spectral statistics and their applications to spin glasses & neural networks
- Awarded highest possible mark
- P. Mühlbacher, "Protein Docking", 2015
- Report with a focus on numerics and an efficient implementation
- P. Mühlbacher, "Elliptic Curves and their Applications in Public Key Cryptography", 2012 (in German)
- Won the Dr. Hans-Riegel award, worth €600

EXTRACURRICULARS

Languages

- English (fluent), German (native), French (basics), Russian (basics), Chinese (basics)
- Taught two German language courses to ~15 students for a year

Programming

- Python (NumPy, SymPy, Jupyter notebooks, dynamically fetching data from websites)
- Java (Processing)
- LaTeX
- Web (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, some SQL)
- Git

Other Activities

- Former gymnast
- Following developments in Machine Learning (set up a group of ~30 students in Cambridge to share materials)
- Peer-reviewed for Discrete Applied Mathematics